בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is דף מ. Daf Mem.
As I said, we have now moved from שהייה shehiya issues to
real serious בישול bishul issues. And yesterday we established the idea of
a difference between using heat and using fire, which is דאורייתא, de'oraita,
and the sun, בישול חמה, bishul chama, is not a problem. And
the בבלי Bavli distinguishes between תולדות חמה toldos chama and תולדות אור.
toldos or. תולדות אור Toldos or is similarly possibly, it seems like
even דאורייתא, de'oraita, the idea of putting the egg by the hot
water pot. תולדות חמה Toldos chama is certainly not biblical; whether it's
rabbinic or not is debated, because it could be worse than חמה
chama because it could be confused with תולדות האור. toldos ha'or. So
that was the key issue there. Then we move on to, and
as we also saw about the egg by the kettle, that it
seems like you do not need to have something directly on a
fire in order for it to be בישול דאורייתא, bishul de'oraita, at
least that's the way רב יוסף Rav Yosef interpreted the משנה. Mishnah.
Now we go on though to the fact that the משנה Mishnah
says that when they put this pipe of cold water through the
hot springs of טבריה Tverya to heat up, that the rabbis said
that that was forbidden. They were going to treat that water—it's a
little unclear whether the water was the problem ערב שבת erev Shabbos
and was a type of הטמנה, hatmanah, or the problem was on
שבת Shabbos and they were heating it up with the hot water
which was תולדות חמה. toldos chama. But either way, the rabbis said
we're going to treat the water like it was heated up on
שבת, Shabbos, and therefore you can't use it for bathing or for
drinking, because stuff that you did a מלאכה melachah with on שבת
Shabbos you can't benefit from. And if you did it on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, then it's water you heated up on יום טוב
Yom Tov which you can use for drinking but not for bathing.
And that's going to get us into the interesting discussion of why
can't you heat up water on יום טוב Yom Tov for bathing?
Isn't that like a bodily need and so on? So we pick
up with אמר רב איקא, Amar Rav Ika, it's the last of
the narrow lines on ל"ט ע"ב. lamed tes amud beis. And the
question that the בבלי Bavli is dealing with is that it sounds
like if the water was heated up ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, that
would be okay, because it's only like water that was heated up
on שבת. Shabbos. But we know that even if you heat up
water ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, you can't bathe your whole body with
it. And if we're talking about just your face and your hands,
then that should be okay on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and it
says that it's not okay on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So what
is that category of something that it's okay ערב שבת erev Shabbos
but not okay on שבת Shabbos and also not okay on יום
טוב? Yom Tov? So let's take a look. אמר רב איקא בר
חנינא, Amar Rav Ika bar Chanina, להשתטף פני כל גופו עסקינן. lehishtatef
pnei kol gufo askinan. We're talking about not immersing your whole body,
but basically showering, bathing your whole body by pouring water over it.
Okay? And that's והאי תנא הוא דתניא, ve'hai tanna hu detanya, it's
the following תנא tanna which is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the
following ברייתא. beraisa. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, beraisa, לא
ישתטף אדם כל גופו בין בחמין בין בצונן דברי רבי מאיר. lo
yishtatef adam kol gufo bein bechamin bein betzonen divrei Rabbi Meir. A
person should not take a shower with his whole body, splash water
on his whole body, whether hot water or cold water, that's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is really
extremely strict; even cold water he doesn't want you to do—maybe if
you start out in cold water you'll move to hot water, maybe
because, you know, you'll come to, I don't know, use towels and
wring out towels, not clear what רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position is—very
strict. רבי שמעון מתיר, Rabbi Shimon matir, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says,
"No, it's okay, you can even use hot water," presumably water that
was heated before שבת, Shabbos, obviously not water heated on שבת. Shabbos.
So although they said you cannot take a bath of hot water,
but you can take a shower. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda splits,
בחמין אסור בצונן מותר, bechamin assur betzonen muttar, hot water is forbidden,
cold water is permissible. So how does this solve our problem? In
the following way. We're talking according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. According
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if you heat water before שבת, Shabbos,
you can take a shower with it. But you cannot bathe with
it; you cannot take a bath with it. So this water that
you ran through, they ran through the חמי טבריה, chamei Tverya, it's
like water that was heated on שבת. Shabbos. So because if it
were water just from heated before שבת, Shabbos, you could shower with
it. Because it's water that was like heated on שבת, Shabbos, you
can't get any benefit from it; you can't drink from it, you
can't shower from it, and so on. Also on יום טוב Yom
Tov it would be like water that was heated on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So water heated on יום טוב Yom Tov you can
use for your hands and face, but similarly the same way you
cannot use for your whole body. So that's how we get this
type of a thing which is, had it been done ערב שבת
erev Shabbos it would have been okay according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon to shower your whole body, but on שבת Shabbos no good,
and for יום טוב Yom Tov as well. If it were hands
and face it would be okay, but because it's for your whole
body, it's not good. So that's how we find this interesting little
middle space. But what's more interesting for us is the idea that
on יום טוב Yom Tov what we are asserting is you cannot
heat water for your whole body and you also can't heat water
even for, not just to bathing your whole body, but even for
shower. Now why, number one? And number two, on ערב שבת erev
Shabbos you cannot, even water that was heated ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
you can't bathe your whole body, and there's a debate here even
showering. And the reason for the ערב שבת erev Shabbos is clear.
The reason for the ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, what's the big deal,
it was all heated before שבת? Shabbos? So that, as I said
and the גמרא Gemara is going to say later, they had all
these bathhouses. If we're going to allow you to take a bath
with hot water on שבת Shabbos from water that was heated before
שבת, Shabbos, people will wind up heating it up. on שבת Shabbos
and they'll say it was from before שבת Shabbos or accidentally you
know come to it or they'll intentionally do it and they'll have
somebody else do it for them whatever it will be but we
don't want you taking hot baths on שבת Shabbos it'll lead to
even from water from before שבת Shabbos it'll lead to it'll lead
to heating the water on שבת. Shabbos. The bigger question is why
not a hot shower on יום טוב Yom Tov why not a
hot bath on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Isn't that something that is
a צורך כל הגוף tzorach kol haguf it's a bodily need which
you're allowed to do? I mean for God's sake you know for
a long period and even now not just a long period people
who smoke think they're allowed to smoke on יום טוב Yom Tov
because they say oh you know it's like there was a time
where it was actually believed it was good for health. But even
now people will smoke on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you can't
take a hot bath on יום טוב? Yom Tov? You can't take
a hot shower on יום טוב? Yom Tov? What's that about? What's
why should that be a problem? I mean you're allowed to use
fire. So here there's a debate between תוספות Tosfos and the רמב"ן.
Ramban. The רמב"ן Ramban says the reason is it's a type of
a לא פלוג. lo pelug. Since on שבת Shabbos once we started
saying hot baths are off limits so even water from before שבת
Shabbos so the same way we're going to say water from before
שבת Shabbos hot baths are out we're going to say water heated
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. That's a pretty strange לא פלוג lo
pelug because you know יום טוב Yom Tov I mean so many
things are permissible with heat and so on and with fire why
would you do such a לא פלוג? lo pelug? That's what the
רמב"ן Ramban says. תוספות Tosfos says no. If you take a look
at the תוספות Tosfos ובית הלל מתירים u'Beis Hillel matirin
תוספות Tosfos says one minute
yeah four lines after the words ובית הלל u'Beis Hillel he says
בשם ריב"א beshem Riva דרחיצה אינה אלא לתענוג de-rechitza eina ela le-taanug
ואסורה כמו מוגמר ve-assura kmo mugmar משום דאין שוה לכל נפש mishum
de-ein shava le-chol nefesh
that the reason is that we're assuming that bathing your whole body
in hot water is a type of a pleasure and a תענוג
taanug that is not even like a common you know physical bodily
bodily pleasure like food. It's something that's only like a you know
very you know like a very small segment of the population wants
like burning incense. So therefore because it's something that is not שוה
לכל נפש shava le-chol nefesh it's not a very common type of
a physical bodily pleasure it's only some therefore it's not allowed on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now this תוספות Tosfos is a very good
תוספות Tosfos because if you say like the רמב"ן Ramban that it's
לא פלוג lo pelug then okay it's rabbinic restriction you can't take
a bath or shower like we see even showers are debated here
you can't do your whole body in hot water on יום טוב
Yom Tov why? There's no good reason but לא פלוג lo pelug
the rabbis said it end of story. But according to תוספות Tosfos
it's only because of an assessment that this is not something that
is a common bodily need or pleasure and therefore nowadays when you
live in places where you bathe on a regular basis and it
is a common bodily pleasure and need it actually should be fine.
And and there are definitely פוסקים poskim that say and and the
שמירת שבת Shemiras Shabbos it's interesting to track him because I think
in one place he has a huge footnote I think he might
change his position over time. But anyway I believe he also there
actually says that certainly you know bathing may be a little bit
different because bathing maybe it is a little bit more like this
גזרה gezeira and so on but certainly a hot
shower nowadays for people that bathe regularly and shower regularly should not
be a problem on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And I take a
hot shower on יום טוב. Yom Tov. I actually started by just
first day first day first I first I thought I would only
do it on יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni but now I've
started doing it now maybe I've gotten more I don't know fastidious
over time or whatever but now I take a hot shower even
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Thing you do have to be careful
about like about the סחיטה sechihta with your hair and סחיטה sechihta
with the towel so sort of like let your hair drip dry
or just like pat it dry. But anyway this גמרא Gemara assumes
you cannot do a hot shower or hot bath on יום טוב
Yom Tov question why is it rabbinic or is it because of
an assumption that it's not a common bodily need and if it's
the latter then obviously that can change radically nowadays. Yes Michael.
First of all about the סחיטה sechihta is the סחיטה sechihta when
you're actually washing or is it when you're getting out not when
you're more?
Maybe I'm not going to yes
I'm not going to get into it. The other question is though
but don't we also have the problem about חמי טבריה בשבת chammei
Teveria b'Shabbos right don't we all have like these hot water urns
that you know you plug it in before שבת Shabbos you fill
it up and then it you know how we all have hot
water on שבת? Shabbos?
I don't understand normally if you put something up from before שבת
Shabbos it's allowed to finish cooking and the hot water's allowed to
remain hot.
Right but it's always like you know it's still always hot I
mean so the חמי טבריה... chammei Teveria...
You're allowed to use hot water you just can't bathe in hot
water I don't understand. No we're saying חמי טבריה chammei Teveria was
a particular problem. Why were they particularly strict by חמי טבריה? chammei
Teveria? It could be that it was a type of a הטמנה
hatmana which is a problem even on ערב שבת erev Shabbos so
as opposed to putting something on the fire to continue to cook
on שבת Shabbos is okay but הטמנה hatmana is not good. Or
it's possible that that seems to be the בבלי Bavli read but
it's possible an alternative read not necessarily from the בבלי Bavli and
maybe more obviously the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is no maybe they turned on
the cold water on שבת Shabbos and it ran through and it
got heated ממש mamash on שבת Shabbos it wasn't from before שבת
Shabbos it got heated ממש mamash on שבת. Shabbos.
Yes I'm trying to understand that ערב שבת erev Shabbos problem.
Okay. All right. Yes Rivka.
Wouldn't they be permitted to go to מקוה mikveh Friday night?
Oh so that's a good question. So let's talk about that for
a minute. So here if it's been heated from ערב שבת erev
Shabbos you cannot bathe on שבת Shabbos with it because of this
idea of this like לא פלוג lo pelug of of you know
גזירת מרחצאות gezeiras merchata'os of bathhouses. So I should say, let me
say two things. First of all, first of all, so I want
to get to רבקה'ס Rivka's point. So one thing is in אשכנזים
Ashkenazim that leads to even for not heated water. אשכנזים Ashkenazim do
not have a מנהג minhag from going back about a thousand years
not to not to immerse the whole body in water even in
cold water, which is clearly not in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara was just in hot water and a lot of that had
to do with concerns about, you know, get out of the, you
know, first of all, סחיטה s'chita of your hair, סחיטה s'chita of
the towels, you'll squeeze it or if you're not in an עירוב
eiruv and let's say you're doing a you're doing a you're swimming
in an ocean or whatever well swimming in an ocean is a
problem because is another problem. But let's say anyway whatever it is,
you know that you'll come to carry the water on your body
if you're walking outside with it on you. So anyway so אשכנזים
Ashkenazim already going back a good thousand years have a מנהג minhag
not to not to immerse their whole body even in cold water.
ספרדים Sefardim do not have that מנהג minhag and ספרדים Sefardim actually
will swim on שבת Shabbat like in a swimming pool. So we'll
discuss actually that and other problems about swimming coming up later in
today's דף. daf. But that's one way in which this extends. And
the other thing that רבקה Rivka asked, an excellent question: how do
women go to the מקוה mikvah on Friday night? Isn't that water
that's hot, heated water? And you're not supposed to immerse your whole
body in heated water on שבת. Shabbat. So there's a whole long
string of פוסקים poskim that deal with that and basically they try
to come up with various justifications. Like some say well maybe it's
only really hot water and maybe the water there is more like
warm and not hot. Anyway at the end of the day they
basically just like turn a blind eye to it because they basically
say you know it's necessary to do if you want women to
use the מקוה mikvah on שבת Shabbos
and so the question is raised but the interesting thing is nobody
says you have to stop the practice. Okay they acknowledge it's a
problem but nobody says you have to change the practice as a
result of that. But yes that is an interesting point and there
is a lot of discussion about reconciling that. Yes.
Is it only for men who go to the מקוה mikvah also
on שבת? Shabbos?
Yes that's a good point. Yeah I don't know I don't know
if they're the same sort of allowance or the implicit allowance of
hot water is true. I don't know about men that go to
the מקוה mikvah daily whether they also go to a heated מקוה
mikvah on שבת. Shabbos. I don't know. Good question.
But even for cold water the אשכנזים Ashkenazim that's true.
That's true. So even for אשכנזים Ashkenazim for the idea of not
immersing fully in cold water, yeah I think that there's an interesting
point. Yeah I guess that's true that they also have an implicit
exception there for going into the מקוה. mikvah. It's a good point.
It's a good point.
Okay alright. So those are some of the issues. Don't immerse your
whole body on hot water on שבת Shabbos even from heated from
before שבת Shabbos as we just said. For the אשכנזים Ashkenazim that
would even be a shower as we said להשתטף leishtatef although רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees but according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda for
אשכנזים Ashkenazim it's even if not hot water. And on יום טוב
Yom Tov don't do it on יום טוב Yom Tov which is
a little even which is strange. Why not? And as we said
that might be different nowadays when it's seen clearly as a more
greater common bodily need. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda three lines down in the wide
lines. אמר רב חסדא מחלוקת בכלי. Amar Rav Chisda machlokes b'kli. This
debate about water that was about you know about using water that
was heated up that was when it was heated up when it
was in a vessel and then it's more likely that you'll come
to you know even if it was heated before שבת Shabbat it'll
look like it was you know you'll come to cases of being
heating it up on שבת. Shabbat. אבל בקרקע דברי הכל מותר. Aval
b'karka divrei hakol mutar.
If the hot water is somehow in the ground then it is
more permissible because somehow that'll lead less if it was heated before
שבת Shabbat it'll less likely that it'll lead to a case of
doing it on שבת. Shabbat. Not exactly clear why especially since one
of the גזירות gezeros was גזירת מרחצאות gzeiras merchazaot which was sort
of like things built into the ground these bathhouses. Anyway the גמרא
Gemara challenges it. גמרא Gemara says אמעשה דאנשי טבריה בקרקע הוי ואסרו
להו רבנן? amaisa d'anshei Tverya b'karka havay v'asru lehu rabbanan?
One minute the story with the people of טבריה Tverya was a
case that the water was in a pipe that was going through
the hot springs and that was in the ground and that was
from presumably the גמרא Gemara here is reading it like the גמרא
Gemara before that it was an ערב שבת erev Shabbat problem and
the rabbis forbade it even though it was ערב שבת. erev Shabbat.
אלא אתמר הכי אתמר מחלוקת בקרקע. Ella itmar hachi itmar: machlokes b'karka.
This debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that
it's allowed if it's it's allowed for a shower that's in the
ground. אבל בכלי Aval b'kli if it was in a vessel דברי
הכל אסור divrei hakol assur everybody would say it's forbidden because then
presumably you know a vessel is a type of thing that you
more easily put on a fire. So somebody sees you with hot
water in a vessel pouring it over your body even if it
was heated before שבת Shabbat that's more of a likelihood that you'll
come to heat it up on שבת. Shabbat. Okay. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יהודה. Amar Rabba bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. This is very important because this means you not only
can you not bathe with water heated before שבת Shabbat you cannot
shower with water heated before שבת. Shabbat. הלכה כרבי יהודה. Halacha k'Rabbi
Yehuda. אמרי ליה רב יוסף בפירוש שמיע לך או מכללא שמיע לך?
Amrei lei Rav Yosef: befeirush shemi'alkha o mikhlala shemi'alkha? Did you hear
it explicitly or are you implying it from something from some other
statement or from some other observation? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
כללא? mai klala? What would be the inference like it's not explicit
but it's from a general thing that you inferred? דאמר רבי תנחום
אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי ינאי אמר D'amar Rabbi Tanchum amar Rabbi
Yochanan amar Rabbi Yannai amar רב Rav או אמר רבי o amar
Rabbi
כל מקום שאתה מוצא שנים חולקין ואחד מכריע kol makom she-ata motzei
shnayim cholekin ve-echad machriya that whenever there are two people disagree and
one person is a compromise position הלכה כדברי המכריע halakha k'divrei hamachriya
you go by the compromise. And here you have that: רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says you can't do even cold water, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says you can even shower with hot water from pre-שבת, Shabbat,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says hot water no, cold water yes.
So maybe you said, oh, he's a compromise position, we go like
him. חוץ chutz and the exception is מקולי מטלניות, mikulei matlaniyot, you
might remember this, the type of rags that are used for like,
you know, discarded cloth that are used for various rag purposes and
pot holders and whether they still are מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. שאף
על פי שרבי אליעזר מחמיר ורבי יהושע מקיל ורבי עקיבא מכריע she-af
al pi she-Rabbi Eliezer machmir ve-Rabbi Yehoshua makeil ve-Rabbi Akiva machriya although
there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was strict and treated them like a
for that it could become טמא, tamei, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
was lenient, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva split the cases, אין הלכה
כדברי המכריע. ein halakha k'divrei hamachriya. There we don't go like רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the compromise. Why? חדא דרבי עקיבא תלמיד הוה, chada
de-Rabbi Akiva talmid hava, number one he was a student of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, so he doesn't count
as a compromise position. ועוד הא הדר ביה רבי עקיבא לגבי רבי
יהושע. ve-od ha-hadar be-Rabbi Akiva legabei Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
reversed himself. So we won't go into reminding ourselves what that case
was, but actually it did come up just a few, just about
two weeks ago. But anyway, maybe that's why you're פוסק posking like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here about no hot showers because he's a
compromise. So the גמרא Gemara says: ואי מכללא מאי? ve-i mikhlala mai?
So and if it was an inference what difference does it make?
It's still a good פסק. psak. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
maybe you didn't infer correctly. דילמא הני מילי במתניתין. dilma hani mili
be-matnitan. Maybe when do we go like a compromise position, when it's
in the משנה? Mishna? אבל בברייתא לא. aval be-braita lo. But maybe
when we say we always go like the מכריע machriya that's not
in a debate in a ברייתא, braita, maybe only a debate in
a משנה. mishna. Which is pretty funny because you would assume the
reason you go by a מכריע machriya is, you know, why not
adopt a compromise position? It's midway between the two extremes. The fact
that we would distinguish between a משנה mishna and a ברייתא braita
would say that maybe it's not just the substance of the position
is midway, maybe somehow רבי Rabbi is implicitly by framing it in
a certain way in a משנה mishna indicating who he wants the
הלכה halakha to be like, and therefore there's less evidence by a
ברייתא braita that would be less the case. Also I should mention
there's a long תוספות Tosafos here, it's not even so long, there's
longer תוספות Tosafoses that discuss how do you define a compromise position?
Not every position that happens to be midway between the two extremes
is logically a compromise. Right, a compromise is that you hear part
of one argument and part of the other and this is some
hybrid of the two. You could have a midpoint position which is
not a compromise position. So תוספות Tosafos tries to figure that out.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says if it was because of a
ברייתא, braita, maybe we shouldn't go because this is a ברייתא. braita.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה אנא בפירוש שמיע לי, amar
lei ana be-feirush shemi' li, I heard explicitly that we rule like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So this is the rule, that on שבת
Shabbat you cannot bathe fully immersed your body in hot water even
from before שבת Shabbat or take a shower with hot water even
from before שבת. Shabbat. Now we're going to discuss what about things
that are somewhere between that and hands and face.
איתמר, itmar, it was taught. חמים שהוחמו מערב שבת. chamim she-uchmu me-erev
Shabbat. Water that was heated before שבת. Shabbat. רב Rav אמר למחר
רוחץ בהם כל גופו איבר איבר. amar le-makhar rokhetz ba-hem kol gufo
eiver eiver. Ah, you can't take a shower and you can't take
a bath, but here's what you can do: you can do each
limb separately. First you do your right arm, then your left arm,
then your right leg, then your left leg. So eventually you get
your whole water body bathed with hot water but not all at
one time. That's what רב Rav says. ושמואל אמר לא הותרו לרחוץ
אלא פניו ידיו ורגליו. ve-Shmuel amar lo hutru lirkhotz ela panav yadav
ve-raglav. No, all, the only thing they said was hands, face and
feet. Right, so you have like, you know, the question about the
middle. You say you can't do your whole body whether bathing or
showering, you can do hands, feet and face. Well what about something
between those two extremes? Other parts of your body, doing it sequentially,
not at one time. So רב Rav says it's all okay, and
שמואל Shmuel says no, only the other extreme, only hands and face
and feet.
מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you on רב's Rav's position. חמים שהוחמו מערב
שבת, chamim she-uchmu me-erev Shabbat, if the water was heated before
שבת, Shabbat, למחר רוחץ בהם פניו ידיו ורגליו. le-makhar rokhetz ba-hem panav
yadav ve-raglav. You can do your face and hands, hand, hand, feet
and face, face hands and feet. אבל לא כל גופו, aval lo
kol gufo, not your whole body. תיובתא דרב, tiyuvta de-Rav, it's a
contradiction to רב Rav somehow because it's emphasizing that the first part,
that that's the only thing that's permitted. So אמר לך רב: amar
lekha Rav: לא כל גופו בבת אחת. lo kol gufo be-vas akhas.
You can't do your whole body at once, right, presumably also because
not your whole body might even mean not your whole body sequentially.
So רב Rav says no. Not your whole body means not your
whole body at once. אלא איבר איבר. ela eiver eiver. You can
do individual limbs and then eventually get to your whole body. So
the גמרא Gemara says: והא פניו ידיו ורגליו תניא. ve-ha panav yadav
ve-raglav tanya. It says you can only do your face and hands
and feet. כעין פניו ידיו ורגליו. ke-ein panav yadav ve-raglav. It means
like your face and hands and feet, individual limbs one at a
time, not your whole body at once. That's what it means. תא
שמע, ta shema, let's try again. לא התירו לרחוץ בחמים שהוחמו מערב
שבת אלא פניו ידיו ורגליו. lo hitiru lirkhotz be-chamim she-uchmu me-erev Shabbat
ela panav yadav ve-raglav. It says they only allowed you from water
heated before
שבת Shabbat your face, hands
and feet. obviously hands, face and feet are the things that get
most exposed and most dirty, so there's one read to say that
is the only thing they allowed and the other is no, as
long as it's not like a bath, as long as it's individual
limbs at a time, that's enough, yes.
I'm still not understanding what the problem is.
The problem is that it'll lead to heating it on שבת. Shabbos.
Yes, and we'll see that in a minute.
Okay right, but what I'm saying is so you're not going to
heat it if you're only going to wash your hands, face and
feet. Why is it a סחיטה s'chita problem?
It should be a... It is not a סחיטה s'chita problem. It
is a problem that you will come to heat it, that they
had an institution of bathhouses and therefore it was very if you
start taking baths you will very easily come to having heated the
whole water. It's not anytime you use hot water, it's a גזירה
gezaira you'll heat it up. Then we couldn't have hot food on
שבת Shabbos and we couldn't have hot water on שבת. Shabbos. It
specifically was related to the institution of bathhouses, which is what רב
Rav is emphasizing and therefore the whole problem is the entire body.
Okay so let's see a little bit further. תא שמע, Ta shma,
okay we just did that. Okay, תניא כוותיה דשמואל, tanya k'vosei d'Shmuel,
we taught like שמואל. Shmuel. חמין שהוחמו מערב שבת, Chamin shehuchmu m'erev
Shabbos, if the water was heated ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, למחר רוחץ
בהן פנים ידיים ורגליו, l'machar rochetz bahen panim yadayim v'raglav, the next
day on שבת Shabbos you can use it for your face, hands
and feet, אבל לא כל גופו איבר איבר. aval lo kol gufo
eiver eiver. So this ברייתא braisa explicitly rejects רב. Rav. You cannot
do your whole body even one limb at a time. ואין צריך
לומר חמין שהוחמו ביום טוב, V'ein tzarich lomar chamin shehuchmu b'Yom Tov,
and you don't and it goes without saying that if it was
heated up on יום טוב, Yom Tov, which is bizarre. What do
you mean it goes without saying? As we just said, יום טוב,
Yom Tov, what's the problem? But again, the גמרא Gemara assumes that
takes it for granted that יום טוב Yom Tov also it's not
common to heat up you know like תוספות Tosfos to bathe your
whole body in hot water. It's not considered a legitimate צורך tzorech
of like food is. And therefore if you can't do ערב שבת
erev Shabbos when it's still חול, chol, how much more so can
you not do on יום טוב? Yom Tov? As we pointed out,
for us יום טוב Yom Tov is clearly different than it was
in the
גמרא. Gemara. But anyway that's the גמרא Gemara is applying it to
יום טוב Yom Tov as well. I should say by the way
with all of this being said, the רמ"א Rama פוסק pasken that
it's not just that while you can't do each limb at a
time to get to your whole body, you can do other limbs
other than hands, face and feet. So you can use hot water
for other parts of your body. Meaning you realize though there's still
even if we don't allow רב, Rav, we don't allow every single
limb individually getting to your whole body, the still question is okay
but still is it just hands, face and feet? Let's say I
want to wash my leg, let's say I want to wash my
stomach or something like that, right? So actually the רמ"א Rama says
that actually is okay as well. The whole problem is that you
do each limb at a time and you get to your whole
body and that specifically is what we're rejecting.
Why you can't do one limb then?
Well so we're going to get to that in a minute. So
let's keep on going.
Okay so yes.
In the end we do say a little bit like רב, Rav,
even though right, so we're going to take a look. Okay right.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבה מתני לה להאי שמעתא
דרב בהאי לישנא. Rabba matni lah l'hai shmaita d'Rav b'hai lishna. רבה
Rabba taught the following teaching of רב Rav in the following way.
חמין שהוחמו מערב שבת, Chamin shehuchmu m'erev Shabbos, if they were water
was heated before שבת, Shabbos, למחר l'machar what's the story the next
day? אמר רב רוחץ בהן כל גופו ומשייר איבר אחד. Amar Rav
rochetz bahen kol gufo m'shayer eiver echad. Your whole body and leave
off one limb. But again presumably that could even be washing it
at one time like taking a shower with one arm stuck out
of the door.
Okay so that you can do as long as it's not literally
your whole body. איתיבי, Eisvei, כל הני תיובתא. kol hanei tyuvta.
We asked all of the questions we asked above, which said you
cannot do limb by limb, you can only do your hands, face
and feet, and the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא. tyuvta. In the end
yeah that pretty much indicate not like רב Rav you cannot do
these types of tricks. Now I should say though that still is
different than the רמ"א. Rama. The רמ"א Rama says you can do
individual limbs as long as you don't do your whole body. That's
still different than this case which is you literally do your whole
body at once and keep one arm out of the shower. Let's
say you do each limb at a time and don't do your
whole body, it sounds like from the רמ"א Rama that he would
say that that's okay. He says as long as you could do
individual limbs as long as you don't do כל גופו. kol gufo.
In hot water?
With only obviously with hot water we're talking about hot water. Yeah.
So anyway so that is funny cause you would have thought the
emphasis of גמרא Gemara seems to be getting to just hands, face
and feet that's nothing, but again the רמ"א Rama pushes back a
little bit and does allow other limbs and presumably even multiple other
limbs if you do them one at a time and that רב's
Rav case here would be you're bathing or showering with one arm
stuck out.
Cause you're not talking about רב יהודה Rav Yehuda anymore who said
חמין אסור וצונן מותר? chamin assur v'tzonin mutar? We are talking about
רב יהודה.
Rav Yehuda. So חמין chamin is what's אסור. assur. And within the
context of חמין, chamin, it's only your whole body as and or
what constitutes your whole body here and what's that's exactly the point.
Yes. We're not dealing the אשכנזי מנהג Ashkenazi minhag about cold water
is not here at all we're talking within רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda.
אמר ליה רב יוסף לאביי. Amar lei Rav Yosef l'Abaye. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef said to אביי, Abaye, רבה Rabba who just got
through saying that
Rav said you can do it all except for one limb, so
מי קעביד כשמעתיה דרב. mi ka'avid k'shmaiteh d'Rav.
Did he rule like רב? Rav? I mean he said that רב
Rav said you can do it by leaving one limb out or
so did he actually פוסק pasken do that way in practice? Did
he follow his רבי rebbi רב Rav in this regard? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said that to אביי Abaye
now what רב יוסף Rav Yosef was אביי's Abaye רבי. rebbi. But
why is he saying it to אביי? Abaye? Cause אביי Abaye knew
the practice,
אביי Abaye also learned from רבה Rabba and אביי Abaye knew the
practices of רבה Rabba so therefore רב יוסף's Rav Yosef and and
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said and רבה Rabba had passed away
already. רבא Raba was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva before רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef said to אביי, Abaye, Hey,
you were a student of רבא. Raba. What did he do? Did
he actually practice like רב? Rav? Did he actually take a hot
bath or hot shower and just leave one limb out? So what
did he do that way or not? אמר ליה, Amar Lei, לא
ידענא. Lo Yadana. I don't know. So מאי קא מיבעיא ליה, Mai
Ka Miba'ei Lei, but what was the question, says the גמרא? Gemara?
פשיטא דלא עביד, Peshita Delo Avid, obviously he did not act like
רב. Rav. Why? דאיתותב, De'itosev,
because רב Rav was contradicted by all of this evidence. So of
course that, you know, if רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, if רבא Raba
was paying attention to all of the discussion and all of the
proofs against it, there's no way he could have acted like רב,
Rav, even though that was his רבי's Rebbe פסק. Psak. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא, Dilma, or some take out the דילמא,
Dilma, לא שמיע ליה. Lo Shemia Lei. Maybe, you know what, maybe
he didn't hear of those contradictions, maybe he didn't hear of those
counter proofs. ואילו
שמיע ליה, Ve'ilu Shemia Lei, the גמרא Gemara says, alright, but if
he didn't hear of those contradictions, then ודאי עביד Vaday Avid and
he definitely did do what his רבי Rebbe told him, רב Rav
said. דאמר אביי, De'amar Abaye, because אביי Abaye said, כל מילי דמר,
Kol Mili Demar, all the practices of the master here, רבא, Raba,
אביי's Abaye רבי, Rebbe, רבי, Rebbe, עביד כרב, Avid KeRav, he did
like רב, Rav, which was רבא's Raba רבי. Rebbe. So אביי Abaye
said all of the practices of my רבי, Rebbe, רבא, Raba, he
followed like רב. Rav. Okay, בר מהני תלת, Bar Mehani Telas, except
in three cases דעביד כשמואל, De'avid KiShmuel, he practiced like שמואל. Shmuel.
What were the three? We saw this also before.
מטילין מבגד לבגד, Mattilin MiBeged LeBeged, you can remove ציצית Tzitzis from
one garment to another. ומדליקין מנר לנר, Umadlikin MiNer LeNer, you can
light נרות חנוכה Neiros Chanukah from one candle to the next, right?
We had that before when we did חנוכה. Chanukah. והלכה כרבי שמעון
בגרירה, VeHalacha KeRabbi Shimon BeGireira, we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
when it comes to dragging like a bench or a chair, you
can drag it in a, you know, flower bed or something, as
long as it won't definitely make a furrow, if you're just trying
to move it from one place to another because it's אינו מתכוין.
Eino Miskaven. So you see that he always would rule like רב.
Rav. So what's your problem? If he heard of the counter-evidence, we're
sure he obviously would have dropped the position. And if he didn't
hear of the counter-evidence, of course he did like רב, Rav, because
he always did like רב. Rav. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
דילמא, Dilma, says the גמרא, Gemara, no, I'm sorry, כחומרי דרב עביד,
KeChumrei DeRav Avid, כקולי דרב לא עביד. KeKulei DeRav Lo Avid. We
know that he normally would go like the stringent positions of רב.
Rav. We don't know that he would always go like the lenient
positions of רב. Rav. Okay? So in all these debates where it
said in three cases he went like שמואל, Shmuel, that's when שמואל
Shmuel was lenient. And we said that's a surprise because normally he
would have gone like רב, Rav, which means, but maybe all that
means is he would always go like רב Rav when רב Rav
was strict. We don't know that רבא Raba would always go like
רב Rav when רב Rav was lenient, and here רב Rav was
lenient, okay? So basically we leave it as an open question. Did
רבא Raba go like רב? Rav? If he heard of the counter-evidence,
he obviously did not. If he didn't hear of the counter-evidence, we
still don't know if he went like רב Rav because this was
a leniency of רב. Rav. And we're not certain that רבא Raba
always went like רב Rav when רב Rav was lenient. We know
he always went like רב Rav when רב Rav was strict. We
don't know he always went like when he was lenient. Anyway, what's
clear from the upshot, from the general
sense of the גמרא Gemara is we completely reject רב's Rav position,
and we do not let you do limited time to get your
whole body, we don't let you shower the whole time and leave
one limb hanging out. But as I did say, the רמ"א Rama
does פסקן Pasken you don't, you're not limited to hands, feet, and
face, you can do other limbs, as long as in the sum
total you don't do all of the limbs. And that sounds like
maybe just leaving off one limb. And the difference between that and
the גמרא Gemara must be that the גמרא Gemara you were taking
a shower with one limb out. According to the רמ"א Rama you're
doing individual limbs. But anyway, it is, according to the רמ"א Rama
it's not as restrictive as the impression you would have gotten from
the גמרא. Gemara. Yes?
So just make sure I'm understanding this all right. Because you know
there's different reasons why one takes a shower. There's like, I just
want to feel all nice and shower, then there's like I'm sweaty,
then there's like I fell in the mud. You know what I
mean? So what are we talking about here?
It's not, this is not a יום כיפור Yom Kippur issue, it's
not a תשעה באב Tisha B'Av issue, this is specifically a גזירה
Gzaira that you will come to heat up the water. It does
not matter what your justification is. The only issue would be about
a חולה Choleh cases, even אין בו סכנה. Ein Bo Sakana. If
you have a sick person, that's different, then we waive other rabbinic
restrictions, so a sick person very often might need to take a
bath or shower. That's a different story. But other than that, this
is not like a יום כיפור Yom Kippur issue where it's about
תענוג Taanug versus not תענוג. Taanug. It's about a concern that you'll
heat up the water, and it doesn't matter what your motivation is.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues and says like this. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we get into the source of all of
this, about why even ערב שבת Erev Shabbos is a problem, and
which is the obvious issue of מרחץ, Merchatz, of the
bathhouses. מרחץ שפקקו נקביו מערב שבת. Merchatz ShePikaku Nekavav MiErev Shabbos. If
you had a bathhouse that you stopped up its holes, meaning that
it was not sort of operating
on
שבת, Shabbos, so you know, let me just check רש"י Rashi here.
Right, so basically רש"י Rashi says it means that you would put
a fire below and the fire would come up through holes and
it would heat up the water. So what you did is you
sealed the holes on שבת, Shabbos, so the water wasn't being heated
up.
Like ערב חצות? Erev Chatzot?
Yeah, basically.
Okay, so you did it on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. למוצאי שבת
רוחץ בו מיד. LeMotzaei Shabbos Rochetz Bo Miyad. You can use it
immediately מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbos because the water was not heated up
on שבת Shabbos and therefore it is not a problem. פקקו נקביו
מערב יום טוב pakiku nekavav m'erev yom tov
and similarly if you closed it up on ערב יום טוב, erev
yom tov, למחר lemachar on יום טוב yom tov itself, not even
on מוצאי יום טוב, Motzoi yom tov, on יום טוב yom tov
נכנס ומזיע ויוצא ומשתטף בבית החיצון. nichnas u'meize v'yotzei u'mishtatef b'veis hachitzon.
You can go in and you cannot actually use the hot water.
This is again assuming you cannot use hot water on יום
טוב. yom tov. But you can go in and you can get
a שוויץ. shvitz. You can do like, you can take you know
from the steam, you can steam
up, and now this sounds like it's only something they allowed on
יום טוב. yom tov. Maybe they were more lenient and allowed the
שוויץ. shvitz. תוספות Tosafos actually makes it sound... the previous תוספות Tosafos
said that they assumed that bathing in hot water was not a
common need. They would still assume that maybe taking a steam bath
was more of a common need. But anyway, but as long as
the stuff is stopped up from before שבת, Shabbos, we will see
from or from before יום טוב. yom tov. You're not heating it
up on יום טוב yom tov itself or on שבת Shabbos itself.
We will see that even when they disallowed bathing your entire body
in hot water on שבת, Shabbos, they would initially they did allow
taking like a steam bath like you know having doing a שוויץ,
shvitz, doing a steam. That they would allow if the water was
heated before שבת. Shabbos. Let's take a look. And you can go
and then you rinse yourself in the בית החיצון. beis hachitzon. That's
the outer room outside of you know the sauna where you would
pour cold water on your
body. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. מעשה במרחץ של בני ברק.
Maaseh b'merchatz shel Bnei Brak. There was a story in the bathhouse
in בני ברק. Bnei Brak. שפקקו נקביו מערב יום טוב. shepikiku nekavav
m'erev yom tov. They stopped up the holes ערב יום טוב. erev
yom tov. למחר נכנס רבי אלעזר בן עזריה ורבי עקיבא והזיעו בה
lemachar nichnas Rabi Elazar ben Azarya v'Rabi Akiva v'heziu bah so and
the next day they went into, maybe this was the day after
they stayed up all night on פסח Pesach with the סדר, Seder,
right? Anyway, so the next day they went in והזיעו בה v'heziu
bah and they took a nice sauna. ויצאו ונשתטפו בבית החיצון v'yatzu
v'nishtatefu b'veis hachitzon and then they went into the outer chamber and
they poured cold water over their bodies. אלא שחמין שלו מכופין בנסרים.
ela shechamin shelo mechupin b'nesarim. And what allowed them to do it,
why they felt that was okay, was because the hot water from
which the steam rose was covered with planks. Now why is that
different? Because remember they're assuming that on יום טוב yom tov you
can't even bathe in hot you can't bathe in hot water on
יום טוב. yom tov. So but they're allowing you to do a
steam. So now there's obviously a concern. The way you get steam
is by heating up water. So if you've got the hot water
maybe and you're allowing a steam maybe they'll also come to bathe
in it. So they said, ah that was okay actually because the
hot water was covered with planks and it rose through you know
the cracks in the planks and therefore they had no access to
the hot water so they weren't concerned about the actual bathing in
the hot water.
Like a sauna.
Exactly, exactly like a sauna. So כשבא הדבר לפני חכמים kshebah hadavar
lifnei chachamim
when it came in front of the sages, אמרו amru they said
אף על פי שאין חמין שלו מכופין בנסרים. af al pi she'ein
chamin shelo mechupin b'nesarim. It would be allowed even if it were
not covered with planks. As long as it's just doing a steam
bath and not actual bathing it's okay. Now of course on יום
טוב yom tov you can hear the difference. Maybe if it and
it could be a time where they believed that bathing in hot
water was like a you know delicacy type of a thing and
was not a common pleasure. But therefore not allowed to heat water.
Whereas you know with where a steam was okay. If it were
on you know... so therefore if you were to heat up the
water for steaming that wasn't... that's what תוספות Tosafos said. On שבת,
Shabbos, although this is emphasizing יום טוב, yom tov, but that type
of a distinction on שבת Shabbos is hard to hear. If there's
a concern that you'll come to heat it up, you know if
we allow you to do some stuff heat it up before שבת,
Shabbos, you'll come to heat it up on שבת Shabbos because of
the whole institution of bathhouses, why wouldn't it be an equal concern
with steaming, you know with a sauna than it would be with
bathing? It's not clear at all. But now the משנה Mishnah is
really distinguishing only between יום טוב. yom tov. But let's take a
look as the גמרא Gemara continues. So גמרא Gemara says like this
or the ברייתא Braisa משנה Mishnah ברייתא Braisa says... ומישרבו עוברי עבירה
umishe'rabu ovrei aveira when the sinners increased, those transgressors, התחילו לאסור. hischilu
le'esor. They began to forbid
even steaming. Okay, and we'll see what that is in a minute.
Even steaming they said is off limits. אמבטיאות של כרכים. Ambatia'os shel
krakim. Now the baths of the of the large cities, מטייל בהן
ואינו חושש. metayel bahen v'eino choshesh. You can walk through them and
you don't have to be concerned. Meaning, as long as you're not
going to sit in the sauna, you're just walking through and you're
getting some of the nice steam that's okay. But sitting in the
sauna that would be forbidden. So a second stage came where they
said even steaming is off limits, even the sauna's off limits, but
they still let you sort of walk through and get a little
incidental
benefit. Of of the big cities because the small cities the bathhouses
would be more small and the steam would be more contained and
that would be like going into a sauna. All right, so now
it says like this, מאי עוברי עבירה? mai ovrei aveira? What does
it mean the sinners increased? What's the case? דאמר רבי שמעון בן
פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא. d'amar Rabi Shimon
ben Pazi amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kapara. בתחילה היו
רוחצין בחמין שהוחמו מערב שבת. b'techila hayu rochtzin b'chamin shehuchmu m'erev Shabbos.
Now we're going to get to how this whole thing came about.
Originally they said fine, the water is heated before שבת, Shabbos, no
problem, you take a hot bath on שבת. Shabbos. התחילו הבלנים להחם
בשבת. hischilu habalanim lehachaim b'Shabbos. And now you see why it specifically
is a concern about bathhouses because it's not just you private. Like
this is what was bothering Michael. Why do they let me use
hot food? Why do they let me have hot water for my
tea? I'll come to heat up on... specifically about the hot- the
institution of bathhouses, which was a public institution. If you go and
you say the bathhouses can be open on שבת Shabbat as long
as the water was heated before שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so you know
there are people running the bathhouse. They're- sometimes the water wasn't heated
before שבת Shabbat and they'll say "Don't worry, we took care of
it," right? So התחילו הבלנים להחם בשבת, Hitchilu ha-balanim le-hachem be-Shabbat, the
bathhouse attendants would heat up the water on שבת Shabbat and they'd
say "Nah, it was done-" ומערב שבת הוחמו, u-me-erev Shabbat huchamu, "Don't
worry, it's fine, it was all done before שבת." Shabbat. So אסרו
את החמין. Asru et ha-chamin. They said, "Sorry, you cannot take a
bath in hot water on שבת." Shabbat. We're too concerned about the
scenario of it being done on שבת Shabbat and claimed from before
שבת. Shabbat. והתירו את הזיעה, ve-hitiru et ha-zei'ah, but they still allowed
the שוויץ, shvitz, the sauna. Now again, I don't get it. Why
is that different, right? Same issue, you still have to heat up
water to make the שוויץ, shvitz, but maybe it just was an
assumption that and as we'll see, one of the things going on
here was, like, is it becoming too restrictive? You know, people maybe
still felt, you know, they needed something. You know, they still need-
especially it's a really nice reflection of, like, the reality in, like,
the Roman Empire where bathing was becoming more of a, you know,
a norm because of the Roman bathhouses. Like, you know, in the
Middle Ages, people would sometimes bathe, like, once- you know, even the
Jews would bathe, like, once from ערב שבת erev Shabbat to ערב
שבת erev Shabbat and the non-Jews even less. So, you know, here
it's nice that they feel like, you know, it's gonna be too
restrictive if we say everything is off limits. So we still have
to allow, you know, taking a שוויץ shvitz even though logically the
same concern should be present. So initially they allowed... also, right?
In the sauna, in the שוויץ. shvitz. Yeah, that's a good point.
Right, so not just you mean the health aspect but the cleanliness.
Right.
Hard time to do it during the week either, so that- you
know, so...
Yeah, although you're דווקא davka supposed to bathe ערב שבת erev Shabbat
for כבוד שבת. kevod Shabbat. But it is interesting, again, since- there's
no good reason why, if it's a concern that they'll do it
on שבת, Shabbat, they'll heat up the water, why the שוויץ shvitz
should be more allowed than the bathing. But nevertheless, initially they still
left the שוויץ shvitz alone and that was like the earlier ברייתא
braita that says that, you know, that they went in on יום
טוב Yom Tov to שוויץ, shvitz, but presumably there was a time
even on שבת Shabbat you could go in and שוויץ. shvitz. Okay,
so, that's what they allowed. עדיין היו רוחצים בחמין Adayin hayu rochatzim
be-chamin ואומרים מזיעין אנחנו. ve-omrim me-zi'in anachnu.
And then, so again it's interesting, it doesn't say they would heat
up the water for שוויצינג shvitzing on שבת. Shabbat. No, they would
actually bathe on שבת Shabbat in the hot water and they'd say
"Oh, why am I wet? 'Cause I was in the שוויץ, shvitz,
I was in the sauna." But they would actually bathe. Okay. So
אסרו להם את הזיעה. Asru lahem et ha-zei'ah.
They forbade the- the שוויץ, shvitz, the sauna. והתירו חמי טבריה. ve-hitiru
chamei Tveriah. But what they allowed them to do is, okay, at
least you can go in the hot springs of טבריה. Tveriah. That
doesn't use heat, you know, fire at all. That's okay.
It was all heated before שבת. Shabbat.
It was all heated- it was all חמי בשל חמה chamei beshel
chamah also, whatever. So עדיין היו רוחצים בחמי האור, adayin hayu rochatzim
be-chamei ha-ur, but nevertheless they would do bath- they would take a
bathhouse in fire ואומרים בחמי טבריה רחצנו. ve-omrim be-chamei Tveriah rachatznu. Oh
no, it was- why are we wet? Because we went into the
hot springs. You could only say that if you're in טבריה, Tveriah,
right? I don't know how you could say that elsewhere. Anyway. So
אסרו להם חמי טבריה. Asru lahem chamei Tveriah. They said, okay, you
can't even
use the חמי טבריה. chamei Tveriah. והתירו להם את הצונן. ve-hitiru lahem
et ha-tzonen. Ah, you can still at least do cold water. According
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, they even disallowed cold water, if you
remember from earlier. ראו שאין הדבר עומד להם. Ra'u she-ein ha-davar omed
lahem. Then they said, okay, good, we've like closed up all the
holes, but you know, this is not possible. Like אין הדבר עומד
להם. ein ha-davar omed lahem. This is very powerful, it says like
אין רוב הציבור יכולים לעמוד בו. ein rov ha-tzibbur yecholim la'amod bo.
People really can't tolerate this. It's not- you know, it's too much.
It's creating, you know, too great of a demand on them. התירו
להם חמי טבריה. Hitiru lahem chamei Tveriah. So the big allowance that
they reverse themselves is, okay, חמי טבריה chamei Tveriah you can use.
Okay, which might be interesting though, because it's a big נפקא מינה
nafka mina in Israel with the דוד שמש, dud shemesh, right? If
חמי טבריה chamei Tveriah is in the category of something heated by
the sun, so then you can actually do hot water as long
as it wasn't heated by a fire. Okay, so it's not just
חמי טבריה. chamei Tveriah. וזיעה במקומה עומדת, ve-zei'ah bi-mkomah omedet, but
the prohibition of שוויצינג, shvitzing, that still remains. I really have to
explain- tell you again, unless, you know, there- I imagine it requires
more heat to get a שוויץ, shvitz, a good sauna going, than
it does to get a hot bath, right? So I cannot understand
other than that it was just too restrictive, the logic of saying
זיעה zei'ah should be more lenient than the hot thing if there's
a concern about doing it on שבת. Shabbat. But from here what
you have is that you cannot bathe a full bath, and as
we learned a shower, and maybe each limb individually, on שבת Shabbat
even from water from before שבת Shabbat because of this whole institution
of bathhouses and a concern you'll come to do it on שבת
Shabbat itself. But individual limbs, other types of uses of hot water
are fine. The יום טוב Yom Tov issue is not clearly addressed.
Why is יום טוב Yom Tov a problem? Again, רמב"ן Ramban says
it's a type of לא פלוג, lo plug, which means we have
no latitude nowadays. But the תוספות Tosafot says that it's based on
an assumption that hot water, a hot bath, is not a common
need on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And nowadays that that is different,
many פוסקים poskim allow actually hot showers on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
but you have to again be careful of סחיטה sechitah as I
said. Yes.
There is more social factors, maybe one is more leisurely.
Yeah, that's what דוב Dov said, the social element. That could be.
Yes, Charlie.
I had always thought that the bathhouse... or mostly run by non-Jews,
but this certainly implies that
it- Oh, well it could be, you know, could still be it's
that non-Jews doing a מלאכה Melacha for Jews is still a problem,
although you're right like how many גזירה Gzeira it's it becomes a
גזירה לגזירה, Gzeira l'Gzeira, you know, if at the end of the
road the problem is just a non-Jew doing מלאכה Melacha not a
Jew, why would we make so many restrictions?
Why are you assuming
that, though, that the bathhouses were run by non-Jews?
Well the Romans-
the Romans brought bathhouses to their entire empire and then at this-
But were they run by
the Roman government who owned the bathhouse?
The Roman- not so much the government, but individuals. But we and
we just had a week ago the dispute about the bathhouses. They
did bathhouses and the ונתן להם- v'natan lahem
I understood, but doesn't prove who owned them, who ran them, who
was a- you know, in anyway, it might have been a Roman
who ran it, but he was having the Jews working it. So
I don't know enough about that. That's right.
The גמרא Gemara says it's all correct. There's this whole גזירה Gzeira
really because, you know, you're going to do all this in the
bathhouse and, you know, all that. But so these days we don't
really have bathhouses but no one- I- maybe I'm wrong, people say,
okay, so this doesn't apply?
No, because it's clear from all of the, whatever the historical reason
was, it's clear from all the way it's formulated that nobody says
you can't go to a bathhouse. They say אסור לרחוץ כל גופו
בחמין. assur lirchotz kol gufo b'chamin. Okay, so clearly in the end
the גזירה Gzeira was made- you're right, it could have said it's
limited to bathhouses. But no, in the end they made the גזירה
Gzeira about, you know, any type of a full immersion in hot
water. Yeah.
It would be interesting to know if in טבריה Tverya there were
bathhouses, artificial
bathhouses around the חמי טבריה. Chamei Tverya. That's a good question.
Right, right, in addition to...
Right, I mean they have that now. They have spas built on
the hot springs. Right. So that's- yeah, that's what I sort of
was assuming, but again, it wouldn't explain what they do outside of
טבריה, Tverya, how they could claim- Well maybe this whole episode happened
in טבריה, Tverya, although the first story with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was a בני ברק Bnei Brak story. But right, maybe some of
this about how they, you know, left חמי טבריה Chamei Tverya and
then reversed themselves was a specific טבריה Tverya incident. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, האי מן דעבר אדרבנן
שרי למיקריה עבריינא. Hai man d'avar adirabanan shari l'mikreia avaryana. Somebody who
transgresses a rabbinic restriction, you're allowed to call him a sinner. So
in case you were worried about, yeah, whether you're allowed to call
people certain names, it's appropriate to label somebody a sinner even if
he just transgresses דרבנן. d'Rabanan. How do you know that? כמאן כי
האי תנא, K'man ki hai tana, like the תנא tana that we
just taught. Because the תנא tana says מי שרבו עוברי עבירה, mi
sherabu ovrei aveira, when the sinners, you know, increased. Now and then
it said what was the sin? The sin was was that they
did a- they took a bath and they said they only took
a שויץ. shvitz. But taking a bath, it didn't say the sin
was was that they heated up the water on שבת. Shabbat. The
sin was was they took a bath and they said it was
a שויץ. shvitz. So you see, even if it's only against דרבנן,
d'Rabanan, they're still called עוברי עבירה. ovrei aveira. Okay, now אמבטיאות של
כרכין Ambatiot shel krakhin now we're going back to the next statement
about it. The bathhouses in the large cities. מטייל בהן בחישי. Metayel
bahen b'hishi. You can walk through them and benefit from the steam,
but you're not actually sitting in a sauna so that's okay. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, דוקא כרכין, davka krakhin, that's only of large cities.
אבל דכפרים, Aval d'kfarim, of the villages, לאו, lav, then you can't
walk through the bathhouses. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? כיון דזוטרין נפיש הבליה,
Keivan d'zutrin nafish hevlei, because they're small, there's a lot of steam
in a concentrated place and that's essentially like walking into a sauna.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Now we move on from the גזירה Gzeira of bathhouses, all very
important for us as I said about showering on יום טוב Yom
Tov or taking a hot bath or hot shower even if you've
turned off your hot water heater and whatever there's not other concerns
of using hot water on שבת, Shabbat, which I mentioned briefly yesterday
how to address some of those issues, but nevertheless, hot baths and
hot showers are out with the exception of a חולה choleh person.
Okay, on שבת. Shabbat. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מתחמם אדם כנגד המדורה.
Mitchamem adam k'neged hamedurah. Now we get onto more direct issues about
defining בישול bishul on שבת. Shabbat. So we're really in the heart
of the בישול bishul פרק perek for שבת. Shabbat. Okay. מתחמם אדם
כנגד המדורה ויוצא ומשתטף בצונן. Mitchamem adam k'neged hamedurah v'yotze u'mishtatef b'tzonen.
You can heat yourself by a nice bonfire and go and afterwards,
now that you're all שויץ shvitz because you were in front of
a fire, pour cold water over you. ובלבד שלא ישתטף בצונן ויתחמם
כנגד המדורה. U'bilvad shelo yishtatef b'tzonen v'yitchamem k'neged hamedurah. But don't first
pour cold water over you and then stand in front of the
fire. Why? So it could be because then you're heating up the
water and that might be a בישול bishul problem on the water,
but תוספות Tosafot reads this more in the context of the earlier
discussion, because that's like then רוחץ כל גופו בחמין, rochetz kol gufo
b'chamin, right? It's like first you get the water on you and
then you heat up the water, but in the end it's similar
to, you know, bathing your whole body in hot water. מפני שמפשיר
מים שעליו, Mipnei she'mafshir mayim she'alav, because you warm up, you know,
or the water that is on you, and again, either a בישול
bishul problem on the water or as תוספות Tosafot said connected to
the גזירה Gzeira of bathing.
Isn't it evapor- it's also בישול. bishul. I mean you're not actually
like boiling it, right? The water on you?
Yeah, so we're going to discuss how hot it has to be.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מיחם אדם אלונטית, Meicham adam aluntit, a person
can heat up a like a nice like, um, you know, metal
vessel which is filled with water, ומניחה על בני מעיים בשבת, u'menichah
al bnei me'ayim b'Shabbat,
and you can put it on your stomach on שבת, Shabbat, because
it's like a hot water bottle, right?
ובלבד שלא יביא קומקום של מים חמים ויניחנו על בני מעיים בשבת.
U'bilvad shelo yavi kumkum shel mayim chamim v'yanichenu al bnei me'ayim b'Shabbat.
As long as you don't bring a... I'm sorry רש״י Rashi says
אלונטית aluntis no
no I'm sorry רש״י Rashi says אלונטית aluntis is a towel. I'm
sorry. So I was confusing it with another vessel. So anyway you
can heat up a nice hot a towel and put it on
your stomach on שבת, Shabbat, but don't bring a don't bring a
vessel filled with water, hot water, and put it on your stomach
on שבת, Shabbat, because that's like a hot water bottle. ודבר זה
אפילו בחול משום סכנה, v'davar zeh afilu b'chol mishum sakana, they don't
do it in the weekday because of the סכנה sakana because either
the thing itself or it'll spill and you'll burn yourself or so
on. So what's the problem about doing it besides the סכנה sakana
about doing it on שבת? Shabbat?
So רש״י Rashi says, let's take a look. ונמצא רוחץ בשבת בחמין.
v'nimtza rochetz b'Shabbat b'chamin. The same type of thing. The same way
you can't use hot water on שבת, Shabbat, so now not only
can't you take a hot shower, you can't even put a hot
water bottle on your stomach on שבת Shabbat because maybe it'll spill
and it'll spill over your whole body and then it'll be like
you took a bath on שבת. Shabbat. So we're really getting, you
know, quite many many many גזירות gezeirot built on this idea of
not taking a hot bath on שבת. Shabbat. תוספות Tosafot said, if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he has a different concern. ובלבד שלא
יביא קומקום, u'vilvad shelo yavi kumkum, תוספות Tosafot says פירש כל זמן
שהאלונטית שם, peirush kol zman she'ha'aluntis sham, you can't have the hot
water bottle when you also have the towel there, שמא יפלו המים
על האלונטית ואתי לידי סחיטה, shema yiflu hamayim al ha'aluntis v'ati lidei
schita, because it'll fall on the towel and then you'll squeeze it.
אי נמי לא יביא משום רפואה, ee nami lo yavi mishum refuah,
or because you're not allowed to do רפואה refuah on שבת. Shabbat.
So according to תוספות, Tosafot, says that much of don't have a
hot water bottle, it might break and then it'll be like taking
a shower on שבת, Shabbat, a hot shower, that far we're not
going to go. תוספות Tosafot says there are other concerns. Okay. תנו
רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now we go on. מביא אדם קיתון של מים.
meivi adam kiton shel mayim. Now we get at, now we get
to the real definitions of בישול. bishul. מביא אדם קיתון של מים,
meivi adam kiton shel mayim, you can bring a flask of water
ומניחו כנגד המדורה, u'menicho k'neged hamedura, and put it in front of
a fire. לא בשביל שיחמו, lo bishvil she'yechamu,
not so that it should really get to become hot water, that
would be like cooking on שבת, Shabbat, אלא בשביל שתפיג צינתן, ela
bishvil she'tafig tzintan,
but just that the chill should go out, it should sort of
warm up, not that it should get hot. So what stage is
it considered like you have cooked water? You put it in front
of the fire to warm up so it's not cold, that's okay,
but to get hot, that would be a problem. So what exactly
is the line of the difference? We'll get to. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says מביאה אשה פך של
שמן ומניחתו כנגד המדורה, mevia isha pach shel shemen u'menichato k'neged hamedura,
a woman can take a like a flask of oil and put
it in front of a flame of a fire. לא בשביל שיבשל,
lo bishvil she'yevashel, not that the oil should cook, אלא בשביל שיפשיר,
ela bishvil she'yafsher,
it should dissolve, it should liquefy. Leave the oil around, it'll become
a solid, right, exactly, and now you want it to be, maybe
it was specifically mentioned a woman, maybe it was talking about putting
it like a type of a lotion on the hands. So you
can do it so that it turns into a liquid but not
so much that it heats up and that it cooks. Okay, we
want to know what's the difference, where's the line where it gets
defined as cooking? So we'll get to that. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אשה סכה ידה שמן, isha sacha
yada shemen,
a woman can put oil on her hand ומתחממת כנגד המדורה, u'mitchamemet
k'neged hamedura, and then hold her hand in front of the flame,
in front of the fire, וסכה לבנה הקטן, v'sacha livna hakatan,
and she can put oil on her son, on her child, ואינה
חוששת, v'eina chosheshet, and she doesn't have to be concerned that now
she's in front of the flame and the oil is heating up.
Okay, so now we have the second position and the third position
definitely had a problem with oil. If the oil gets too hot,
it's not good. The final position רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel said, you know, maybe even oil straight in front of
a flame is no good. If it's on your body, you can
be in front of the flame, but the oil straight in front
of the flame might be no good. The first position only mentioned
the water, did not mention how they felt about oil. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. איבעיא להו. iba'ya lehu.
שמן מהו לתנא קמא? shemen mahu l'tanna kamma?
What's the story about oil for the first opinion who just spoke
about water, not oil? So רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו ליתירא, Rabba
v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu l'teira, רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר לאיסורא. Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak amar l'issura. רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef
both say the first position is more lenient, has no problem with
oil. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the first position is more strict,
oil is totally off limits. And now it's going to explain it.
רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו ליתירא, Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu l'teira,
to be lenient. שמן, shemen, oil, אף על פי שיד סולדת בו
מותר. af al pi she'yad soledet bo mutar. Now
here we are getting to what is missing in the earlier statement,
which is the key line at what stage is it considered to
be cooking. And that's יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. יד סולדת
בו yad soledet bo means your hand recoils. If you were to
touch it, it would be so hot your hand would pull back.
That's if you get the water that hot, that's cooking. Now there
are different גרסאות girsaot about this.
הירושלמי ha'Yerushalmi has not יד סולדת, yad soledet, but it says the
opposite, it's not cooking as long as יד שולטת בו, yad sholetet
bo, as long as you can keep your hand in it without
having to pull it out.
So same, similar idea. And another position we'll see is called כריסו
של תינוק נכוית בו, kreiso shel tinok nichveit bo, the stomach of
an infant, if you put some of this hot water on, would
be like burned and scalded. So how hot is that is an
interesting question. Or first of all, there's also two different opinions. One
is based on the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, keeping your finger in that you
can keep it in without having to pull it out. The other
is is that immediately like there's this sort
of sense of recoil.
So exactly where the line is there is interesting and the פוסקים
Poskim try to come up with an exact precise amount. This many
degrees, that many degrees, somewhere between, I don't know, 103 and 115
Fahrenheit is usually the number that they come up with. You know
רב Rav יהודה Yehuda Henkin,
thank
you. רב Rav יהודה Yehuda הרצל Herzl Henkin, he says, is it
יהודה Yehuda הרצל? Herzl? יהודה. Yehuda. Yeah. Anyway, he basically says he
doesn't like the whole idea of trying to come up with like
a degrees because that's not how the חז״ל Chazal would have done
it. They would have said put your finger in, see if you
can keep your finger in, so that's how you should measure it.
But anyway,
like the כזית, Ke-zayit, you're right, exactly. Anyway, so this is the
amount. Now, the interesting thing to note about this is that in
the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara speaks about יד סולדת בו Yad
Soledet Bo in our סוגיא, Sugya, which is about how hot do
you have to heat up liquids that is considered that you've cooked
the liquid. Okay,
we transfer that definition to another area and we say if you
put something in a hot liquid, is it considered cooking or not?
And how hot does the liquid have to be? You understand? So
like, can I put my, you know, bread in my soup if
my soup is very hot? I'm concerned about cooking, although that's בישול
אחר צלי Bishul Achar Tzli or whatever.
How hot is the liquid that a liquid can cook something else?
And we assume it's the same amount about יד סולדת בו, Yad
Soledet Bo, but that I should mention that that is not what
the גמרא Gemara is talking about. What the גמרא Gemara is talking
about directly is how hot to heat up a liquid that is
considered like you cooked the liquid. And that's what our גמרא, Gemara,
right, is discussing. So let's take a look.
So I should say by the way the difference here about the
issue about the infant and the hand in the hot water, right?
I mean, you know, what? Oil? No, no, no, we'll get to
the oil in a minute. No, no, no, I meant the question
about is it that the stomach of the infant scalds or is
it leaving the hand in the water? The question is like,
how are those similar measures? I mean, a hand of an adult
is more, you know, is less sensitive. So obviously so why how
could that be similar to the stomach of an infant? So the
if you read closely the פוסקים Poskim say the difference is the
stomach of the infant as a test is even like a little
bit of the water touches the stomach of the infant. The hand
of the adult is leaving your hand in. Can you leave your
finger in the water, not just touch it? And that's important when
you want to test יד סולדת בו, Yad Soledet Bo, it's not
just to say, oh, I can get my finger in without burning
it. It's the question can you leave it in for like a
few seconds without having to pull it back out? Okay, so anyway,
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that that's the
amount for water, and the question is is oil the same? Now
what should the difference be? Well, here you get to an interesting
question in general about liquids. You know there's all this discussion about
whether there's בישול אחר בישול Bishul Achar Bishul by liquids as opposed
to solids. So part of the question is that solids it's clear
what cooking means. Cooking means that you know it becomes you use
heat and now there's a chemical change and now it becomes from
raw meat to cooked meat or raw vegetables to cooked vegetables, it
becomes edible and so on. But by liquids, if you're dealing with
chicken soup, it's different. Then what you're doing is you're like extracting
from the solids and so on. But if you take just like
a pure liquid, oil or water, what do you mean by cooking?
You don't cook water. You don't cook it, you heat it up,
right? You get it hot. And therefore there's a question: so what
constitutes cooking? So that's why by water cooking might just be getting
it hot. And therefore that might be why there's בישול אחר בישול
Bishul Achar Bishul by liquids. Because once meat is already cooked, it's
cooked. You don't make meat cooked again. Whereas by water if the
definition of cooking is getting it hot, so then when it cools
off, then you get it hot again, so that's בישול אחר בישול
Bishul Achar Bishul if the definition by liquids is more about getting
hot than it is about cooking. And that's why we're going to
see that the גמרא Gemara has an issue why oil might be
different. Oil could be people use hot water. They use hot water
for cooking, they use hot water for making coffee and tea, right?
But hot oil is normally not something, I guess you have hot
oil on a skillet, but using hot oil by itself is not
something that normally is such a meaningful thing. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to raise the possibility that maybe by oil even if
you heat it up it's not considered cooking. Okay, so we're getting
into the interesting category of the status of liquids and what cooking
means by liquids, and that's the גמרא's Gemara issue here around the
issue of oil. So let's take a look.
Yes. What about cleaning a baby on שבת? Shabbat? What are you
doing? You have to use
water.
Right. So you can, it says you can get it warm, you
just can't get it to יד סולדת בו. Yad Soledet Bo. Okay.
Oil, lotion.
Yeah, that's okay. That's okay. So I mean that yeah, yeah. The
only thing is you can't get it really hot. You can't get
it to יד סולדת בו. Yad Soledet Bo. And you wouldn't want
it that hot anyway.
Right, you just warm it up. Right. The concept of boiling point
taken into account?
Yeah, so it doesn't discuss boiling point. יד סולדת, Yad Soledet, whatever
יד סולדת Yad Soledet is, but you
know 110. לרבי יוסי דאמר תרוייהו להיתירא דיינינן. L'rabbi Yose d'amar tarveihu
l'heteira lennan. שנית, Shenit, and first wide line. אף על פי שיד
סולדת בו מותר. Af al pi sheyad soledet bo mutar. Oil even
if you get it to יד סולדת Yad Soledet it's allowed, even
if you get it—so that's not about boiling point. It gets really,
really hot. It's יד סולדת. Yad Soledet. Why? קסבר תנא קמא שמן
אין
בו משום בישול. Kasavar tana kama shemen ein bo mishum bishul. You
don't have cooking by oil. Now again, you use oil to cook
other things, but like I said, by itself heating up oil is
not significant. Heating up water is significant. Heating up oil by itself
is not significant. Oil I have no problem with. אסר רבי יהודה
למימר שמן יש בו משום בישול. Asar Rabbi Yehuda l'meimar shemen yesh
bo mishum bishul. It is considered cooking like heating up water is
considered cooking. והפשרה לא זו היא בישולה. V'hafshara lo zo hi bishulah.
But just sort of putting in front of the fire to liquefy,
that's not a problem. So that you can do, but don't get
it to a point where it's יד סולדת בו. Yad Soledet bo.
ואסר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל למימר, V'asar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel l'meimar,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says שמן יש בו משום בישול. shemen yesh
bo mishum bishul. Yes, it is considered cooking by oil if you
get it hot enough. והפשרה זו היא בישולה. V'hafshara zo hi bishulah.
And putting it in front of the fire to just to liquefy
it, that's already a problem. Now is it automatically cooking? Or maybe
it means that it's a problem because it'll lead to getting that
hot? But anyway, I don't want you to put it straight in
front of the fire. All I'll allow you to do is if
it's on your body you can stand in front of the fire.
So that's the most restrictive. חסנא ביציתא. Chasna b'yatzita.
So that's being lenient. The first approach says Tana Kama says shemen's
totally fine. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר לאיסורא, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
amar l'issura, being strict. The Tana Kama would say שמן אף על
פי שאין יד סולדת בו אסור. Shemen af al pi she'ein yad
soledet bo assur. The first position would say that even less than
יד סולדת בו yad soledet bo is a problem by oil, that
heating up oil is significant and it's not like water. Water you
want to get real hot to make like, you know, tea or
whatever. But oil, maybe even a lower temperature is considered a significant
thing and you're חייב chayav for בישול bishul because קסבר שמן יש
בו משום בישול. kasavar shemen yesh bo mishum bishul. It is considered
cooking. והפשרה זו היא בישולה. V'hafshara zo hi bishulah. Even at a
lower degree temperature, even just becoming liquefied and warm, that's already a
problem. ואסר רבי יהודה למימר הפשרה לא זו היא בישולה. V'asar Rabbi
Yehuda l'meimar hafshara lo zo hi bishulah. Rabbi Yehuda says no, look,
you can get it warm and you can get it liquefied. That's
not בישול. bishul. Getting it יד סולדת, Yad Soledet, that's a problem.
ואסר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל למימר שמן יש בו משום בישול. V'asar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel l'meimar shemen yesh bo mishum bishul. It is
a problem to cook it. והפשרה זו היא בישולה. V'hafshara zo hi
bishulah. And also liquefying it is a problem and don't put the
oil straight in front of the fire even just to liquefy it.
The most you can do is have it on your body and
stand in front of the fire. So the Gemara says according to
this read, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel היינו תנא קמא. hainu tana kama.
Both the first position and last position say you can't even get
it warm. So what's the difference? Right, only the middle position says
that there's by שמן shemen it's an issue of hot as opposed
to warm. So the Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו כלאחר יד. Ika
beinihu k'l'achar yad. The last position now is more lenient. He says
you can stand in front of a fire with it on you,
whereas the first position would say I don't want oil getting warm
at all, even on your body. Very, very strict. Okay. So now
we have the again the interesting category of number one, introducing the
idea that יד סולדת בו, Yad Soledet bo, a key concept for
Shabbat, that we say not only for the Gemara says when is
it considered like you're cooking water when you get it to יד
סולדת. yad soledet. We then apply it to how hot is the
water to has to be to cook other things, but that's not
the focus of the Gemara. And as I said, here by other
things, by the way, by Shabbat, if I put a piece of
raw meat on the fire, I don't transgress right away even when
the raw meat gets hot. I only transgress when it cooks, right?
Because by food it's about cooking, it's about becoming edible and becoming
מאכל בן דרוסאי Ma'achal Ben Drusai or whatever. But that's again the
ways liquids are different is fundamentally by liquid it's more about getting
hot than it is about cooking. So for water it's יד סולדת
yad soledet and then you have the debate about oil. Is it
that it's totally okay? Is it that it's the same as water?
Is it that it's even more strict than water? You have this
range of positions. And as I said, this is also has a
lot to do with why we rule יש בישול אחר בישול yesh
bishul achar bishul by liquids because because by foods it's about cooking.
Once it's cooked, it doesn't cook again. But by liquids it's about
getting hot. Once it cools off, it can still get hot again
and it could be more strict. Okay. So now the Gemara continues.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Oh we
have to end up. Let's read one more line. אחד שמן ואחד
מים. Echad shemen v'echad mayim. We'll just be to conclude, whether oil
or water, יד סולדת בו אסור אין יד סולדת בו מותר. yad
soledet bo assur ein yad soledet bo mutar. If it—so
there's—we rule in the end oil is not more lenient than water,
not more strict, same halacha. If you get it to יד סולדת
בו, yad soledet bo, that's cooking. Less than that, it's okay. והיכי
דמי יד סולדת בו? V'heichi dami yad soledet bo? And what constitutes
יד סולדת בו? yad soledet bo? אמר רחבא כל שכרסו של תינוק
נכוית, Amar Rachava kol shekreiso shel tinok nichveit, as long as the—it's
where you get the stomach of an infant scalded. And again, so
how is that the same as your hand? Your hand is can
you keep your hand in it for a long time? By the
infant it's if even touching it gets a, you know, it's scalding,
then that is the problem. So that is יד סולדת בו. yad
soledet bo. That is the heat that you cannot get water or
other liquids to. It's considered cooking. And the heat that we assume,
although not in this Gemara, that if a water is that liquid
that it will be able to cook other things. So we'll continue
with this tomorrow.